Ahmed Bakkar

Webpage: abakkar.github.io
E-mail: aebakkar@gmail.com
Linkedin.com/in/aebakkar

Profile

I'm a Post-Doctoral Researcher at McGill University's CFD Lab working with Prof. Wagdi Habashi. My research focuses on multi-phase flow modeling with a special interest in droplet dynamics. I have a strong background in developing numerical methods and numerical codes within a parallel environment. I also have experience in HVAC system design and in the field of renewable energy.

Education

PhD in Mechanical Engineering

Feb. 2018

McGill University

Dissertation: "A Finite Element Level-Set Model of Supercooled Large Droplet Dynamics"

M.Sc. in Mechanical Engineering

Sept. 2011

Cairo University

GPA: 3.77

Dissertation: "Humidification - dehumidification of saline water using solar chimney"

B.Sc. in Mechanical Engineering

July 2007

Cairo University

Graduated with Honors (83.2%)

Professional Experience

Post-Doctoral Fellow 2018 - current Research Assistant 2017 - 2018

CFD Lab, McGill University

Supervised 5 graduate students in the development of various numerical codes:

- Extended Finite-Element Method (XFEM) for fluid-structure interactions.
- Smoothed Particle Hydrodynamics (SPH) for high-speed multi-phase flows.
- Gappy Reduced Order Modelling (ROM) for aerospace applications.
- Numerical tools for ice accretion and shedding on helicopter blades.

Junior Mechanical Design Engineer

WS Atkins, PLC 2008 - 2009

2007 - 2008

Dar Al Handasah (Shair and partners)

2007 - 20

- Delivered custom designs for various Ventilating and Air Conditioning (VAC), plumbing, and firefighting systems.
- Negotiated design issues with various design teams, contractor, and clients.
- Provided technical solutions to meet client needs.

Journal Publications

- A. Bakkar, W.G. Habashi and M. Fossati, A Multi-Scale Level-Set Approach for droplet dynamics, In preparation.
- **A. Bakkar**, W.G. Habashi, M. Fossati, and G.S. Baruzzi, *A hybrid Taylor–Galerkin variational multi-scale stabilization method for the level set equation*. Computers and Fluids, 2015. 121: p. 192–205.

Refereed Conference Proceedings

- D. Caraeni, **A. Bakkar** and W.G. Habashi, *An Extended Finite-Element Method for Modelling Fluid-Structure Interaction*, (AIAA 2019-3026791). 2019.
- X. Ciu, **A. Bakkar** and W.G. Habashi, *Multiphase SPH Modeling of Supercooled Large Droplets Dynamics*, 13th SPHERIC International Workshop, Paper 12, Galway, Ireland, June 25-28, 2018.
- A. Kaveh, W.G. Habashi and **A. Bakkar**, *Combining CFD, EFD and FFD data via Gappy Proper Orthogonal Decomposition*, 26th Annual Conference of the CFD Society of Canada, 2018: Winnipeg, Manitoba, Canada.
- **A. Bakkar**, W.G. Habashi, and M. Fossati, *Modeling of Large Droplets Impingement Using a Hybrid Taylor-Galerkin Variational Multi-Scale Stabilized Level Set Method*, (AIAA 2016-1339). 2016.
- **A. Bakkar**, W.G. Habashi, and M. Fossati, *A Hybrid Taylor-Galerkin Variational Multi-Scale Stabilization Method for the Level Set Equation*, in 21st Annual Conference of the CFD Society of Canada. 2013: Sherbrooke, Quebec, Canada.

Honors and Awards

McGill Engineering International Tuition Award

2011 - 2013

McGill University

Outstanding Graduation Project Award

2007

American Society of Heating, Refrigerating and Air-Conditioning Engineers (ASHRAE), Cairo Chapter

Skills

- Developing large code in **FORTRAN** within the **MPI** framework.
- Developed codes in the **Finite-Volume** (FV) and **Finite-Difference** (FD) frameworks.
- Experienced user of the **PETSc**, **MUMPS** and **METIS** libraries.
- Familiar with C++, C, Python and MATLAB.
- Teaching experience: Thermodynamics 1 (MECH 240), Mechanical Laboratory 1 (MECH 362), Turbomachinery and Propulsion (MECH 535), Finite-Element Methods in Computational Fluid Dynamics (MECH 661).
- Language skills: English (native), Arabic (native), French (Conversational, B2)

Extra-curricular Activities

VP Finance 2014 - 2015

Graduate Association of Mechanical Engineering Students (GAMES)

Managed the finances of the organization assuring that it was in good standing.